Guide to the Stanford University, Department of Physics, Records
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Stanford University, Department of Physics, records
1958-1985
1971-1985
SC0433
Stanford University. Department of Physics.
3.25 Linear feet
Research grant files containing abstracts, proposals, correspondence, and budget memoranda; faculty members represented include William Fairbank, Melvin Schwartz, John Dirk Walecka, Robert Hofstadter, and Felix Bloch.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Provenance
Administrative transfer, 1988.
Information about Access
This collection is open for research.
Description of the Collection
Research grant files containing abstracts, proposals, correspondence, and budget memoranda; faculty members represented include William Fairbank, Melvin Schwartz, John Dirk Walecka, Robert Hofstadter, and Felix Bloch.
Access Terms
Bloch, Felix, 1905-; Fairbank, William M., 1917-1989.; Hofstadter, Robert, 1915-1990; Schwartz, Melvin, 1932-2006; Stanford University. Department of Physics.; Walecka, John Dirk, 1932-; Physics--Research.
Collection Contents
- Records, 1958-1985
  - Fairbank/Lipa: JPL (Jet Propulsion Laboratory) Proposal, 1982 May 1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    New Proposal, Unfunded, California Institute of Technology, "A Proposal to Develop a Flight Concept of An Experiment To Measure In A Space Shuttle The Specific Heat of Liquid Helium Through the Lambda Point with Very High Temperature Resolution"
  - Fairbank/Debra: AFOSR 76-2913, 1978 Oct 1-1979 Sep 30 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    (GRAU GAD 1977 Oct-1980 Oct 30), Renewal Proposal to the US Air Force, "The Experimental and Analytical Development of a Sensitive Accelerometer and Gravity Gradiometer"
  - Gifford: ONR (Closed) Office Naval Research), Undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Final Report, "Investigation of Noise and Small-Signal Parameters of R.F. Squid Magnetometers"
  - Litke: DOE, ONR, 1983-1985 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    "A Study of Photon Electron Production in e+e Annihilation" and "Research in High-Energy Physics"
  - Litke, 1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Litke: DOE, 1972-1980 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    "Research in High-Energy Physics"
  - Proposal to NSF, 1976 Jun (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Proposal to NSF for Continuation for a Program of Development and Testing of a Superconductor Electron Accelerator With Recirculation of the Beam and Nuclear Physics Experimentation, Yearian and Schwettman, Physics Dept
  - Little, Undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
    US/Japan Co-operative "Development of the Design of Molecular Structures"
  - Little, Undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
    ONR Unfunded, "Feasibility Study of the Use of Photodiode Arrays in a Fluorescense Immunoassay Technique"
  - Little: ONR 77-C-0631 Closed, 1977 Jun 1-1979 May 31 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    "Structural Considerations in the Design and Synthesis of Polymeric Conductors"
  - Schwartz: NSF 800 - 1640, 1979 Dec 1 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    "High Energy Physics"
  - Susskind/Dimopoulos: DOE Reserch in Theoretical Elementary Particle Physics, 1983 Aug 1-1984 Jul 31 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Fetter: NSF and DMR 8118386 (Div. of Materials Research), 1983-1985 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    "Studies in Quantum Fluids"
  - Fetter: NSF and DMR 8118386 (Div. of Materials Research), 1981-1983 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Fetter: NSF and DMR 8118386 (Div. of Materials Research), 1978-1980 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Wagoner: NASA NSG-7204, Closed, Undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
    "Theoretical Study of the Hard X-Ray Emissions ...."
  - Walecka: NSF, 2FEW404, 79-18046, Closed, 1977-1982 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    "Theoretical Physics"
  - Walecka: Summary of Research Performed, Undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Walecka/Serot: NSF 81-07395, 1983-1984 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    "Studies in Theoretical Physics"
  - Walecka, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    "A Relative Quantum Field Theory of Nuclear Structure"
  - Walecka: DOE, circa 1980 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    "Proposal to Study Accelerations Processes Produced by Excited Atoms"
  - Clifford Will: NASA, NSG 7204, Closed, 1979-1983 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    "Theoretical Analysis of Relativistic Gravitational Experiments"
  - Clifford Will: NASA, NSG 7204, Closed, 1976-1978 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Wojcicki/Schwartz: NSF Supp1. Proposal, 7726029 Closed, 1976-1979 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    "Program in Energy Physics Research"
  - Wojcicki, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    "Budget for a Supplemental Proposal to the NSF for a Program in High Energy Physics"
  - Fairbank/Holm: NSF Research Proposal, 1978 Jan 1 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    "Static and Time-Resolved Magnetic Susceptibilities of Metalloproteins"
  - Fairbank/Madey: AFOSR Renewal Proposal Contract No. F44620--0022, 1975 Oct 1-1976 Sep 30 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    "Fundamental Experiments at Liquid Helium Temperatures," 2 copies
  - Fairbank/Harrison: Renewal Proposal for NSF GI 34778, 1975 May 1-1976 Apr 30 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    "Superconducting Magnetometry for Detection of Heart Disease"
  - Fairbank/Debra: Renewal Proposal for AFOSR 76-2913, 1977 Oct 1-1978 Sep 30 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    "The Experimental and Analytical Development of a Sensitive Superconducting Accelerometer and Gravity Gradiometer"
  - Fairbank/Harrison: Technicon Instruments Corporation, 1975 Apr 1-1978 Mar 31 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    "A Proposal For the Development and Verification of Instrumentation and Computer Processing Techniques for Clinical Magnetocardiology"
  - Fairbank/Harrison: NSF, 1978 Jan 1 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    "The ECG-MCG Relationship: Physiological and Computer Studies"
  - Fairbank/Madley: AFOSR Renewal Contract No. F44620-75-C-0022, 1974 Oct 1-1977 Sep 30 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    "Fundamental Experiments at Liquid Helium Temperatures, two proposals"
  - Fairbank/Giffard: NSF Proposal, 1973 Mar-1974 Feb (Box 5, Folder 1)
    "Search for Gravitational Radiation Using Low Temperature Techniques, Renewal Proposal 1976 Apr 1-1977 Mar 31"
  - Fairbank: NSF Proposal, 1973 Apr 1-1974 Mar 31 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    "Search for Fractional Charge Using Low Temperature Techniques"
  - Fairbank/Debra/Opfer: AFOSR Proposal, 1972 May (Box 5, Folder 3)
    "Experimental Study of Fundamental Problems Associated with Development of a Free Precession HE Nuclear Gyroscope"
  - Fairbank/Everitt/DeBra: NASA Renewal, 1975 Jun (Box 5, Folder 4)
    "Program to Perform a Gyro Test of General Relativity in a Satellite"
  - Fetter: AFOSR Renewal, 1975 Jul 1 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    "Studies in Quantum Fluids and Solids"
  - Little: NASA Renewal, 1971 Oct (Box 5, Folder 6)
    "Effects of Structure Upon the Electronic Behavior of Materials"
  - Litke: DOE, 1976 Jul 1-1977 Jun 30 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    "Study of Photon and Anomalous Electron Production in e+e- Annihilation"
  - Walecka/Giffard: ONR Renewal Proposal, 1978 Jul 1-1979 Jun 30 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    "Investigation of Noise and Small Signal Parameters of RF Squid Magnetometers"
  - A Search for Free Quarks at Pep, Undated (Box 5, Folder 9)
    T. Pun and V. Vuillemin, Lawrence Berkeley Laboratory, B. Gobbi, Northwestern University, A. Litke, Stanford University, and S. Parker and D. Yount, University of Hawaii
  - Hanna/Meyerhof: NSF Proposal Renewal, 1974 Dec 2 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    "Nuclear Structure Investigation with a 15 MeV Tandem Van de Graaff Accelerator"
  - Glavish/Hanna/Schwettman: NSF Proposal, 1971 Apr (Box 5, Folder 11)
    "Program to Develop a Superconducting Heavy Ion Accelerator"
  - Wojcicki/Schwartz: NSF Proposal, 1978 Oct 27 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    "Program in High Energy Physics"
  - Wojcicki/Schwartz: NSF Proposal, 1976-1977 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Wojcicki/Schwartz, 1972 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    "Investigation into Various Aspects of Weak and Electromagnetic Interactions"
  - Walecka: NSF Proposal, 1974 Aug (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Schwettman/Madley: AFOSR Proposal, 1975 Oct 15-1976 Oct 14 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    "Free Electron Laser"
  - Kaplan/Scwettman: NSF Proposal, 1973 Nov 1-1974 Oct 31 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    "Develop a Pion Facility for Cancer Therapy"
  - Turneaure/Will: SAO Proposal, 1977 Oct 1-1978 Feb 28 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    "Performing a Null Gravitational Red-Shift Experiment In Cooperation With The Smithsonian Astronomical Observatory"
  - Wagoner: NSF Proposal, 1974 Sep 10 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    "Theoretical Studies in Gravitation and Astrophysics"
  - Will: NASA Proposal, 1975 Oct 1 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    "Theoretical Analysis of elativistic Gravitational Experiments"
  - Everitt/Worden, 1976 Jun (Box 6, Folder 10)
    "Proposal for a Cryogenic Equivalence Principle Experiment"
  - Schwartz/Wojcicki: NSF Proposal, 1971 Apr 1 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Schiff/Drell: Air Force Renewal Proposal, 1958 Jan 28-1960 Sep (Box 6, Folder 12)
    "High Energy Physics Research" (Budget work, no abstract)
  - Bloch, Proposal for Renewal of Contract, 1968 Jan-1970 Oct (Box 6, Folder 13)
    Objectives of Research: Theoretical study of many-body problems will be continued with particular empahasis on their application to low-temperature phenomena.
  - Bloch, Renewal Contract NONR 225, 1968 Feb-1970 Dec (Box 6, Folder 14)
    Object of Research: Theoretical Study of systems with many particles is to be continued and extended
  - Hofstadter: NSF Proposal, 1972 Nov (Box 6, Folder 15)
    "New Approaches to Dynamic Radionuclides Studies of Vital Organs (Helmet Camera)"
  - Hofstadter, 1973 Feb (Box 6, Folder 16)
    Harshaw Chemical Company, "Study and Preparation of New Scintillator Materials"
  - Hofstadter: DOE Proposal, 1978 Jan 1 (Box 6, Folder 17)
    "Study Acceleration Processes Produced by Excited Atoms"
  - Hofstadter/Yearian: NSF Proposal, 1978 Apr 1-1979 Mar 31 (Box 6, Folder 18)
    "Continuation of a Program of High Energy Physics"
  - Hofstadter: NASA Proposal, 1978 Jan 1-Dec 31 (Box 6, Folder 19)
    "Instrument Development for the Study of High Energy Gamma Rays in Space"
  - Hofstadter/Yearian: NSF Proposal, 1976 Apr 1-1977 Mar 31 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Schiff: Air Force Contract Renewal, 1968 May 1 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    "Theoretical Physics of Fields, Elementary Particles and Collective Phenomena"
  - Schiff: Air Force Contract Renewal, 1966 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    "Supporting the Institute of Theoretical Physics"